Vance Randolph collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Manuscript Materials
  - Reprints of Journal Articles and Reviews
    - "Further Studies of the Reliability of the Maze with Rats and Humans," by Vance Randolph and Walter S. Hunter, reprinted from Journal of Comparative Psychology (August 1924). (Box 18 (oversize), Folder 222)
    - "Jump Rope Rhymes from Arkansas," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Midwest Folklore (III:2) (Box 18 (oversize), Folder 223)
    - "Nakedness in Ozark Folk Belief," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (October-December 1953). (Box 18 (oversize), Folder 224)
    - "The Names of Ozark Fiddle Tunes," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Midwest Folklore (IV:2). (Box 18 (oversize), Folder 225)
    - New York Times book reviews by Vance Randolph: Tales From the Past, Some Tall, Some True (1960); A Treasury to Draw Upon (1960); The Roots Go Deep (1963). (Box 18 (oversize), Folder 226)
    - "A Note on the Reliability of the Maze as a Method of Learning in the Angora Goat," by Vance Randolph and Walter S. Hunter, reprinted from Pedagogical Seminary and Journal of Genetic Psychology (March 1926). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 227)
    - "On the Seasonal Migrations of Dione vanillae in Kansas," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Annals of the Entomological Society of America (June 1927). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 228)
    - Ozark Ghost Stories: Gruesome and Humorous Tales of the Supernatural in the Backwoods of the South, by Vance Randolph, Haldeman-Julius Publications (1944). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 229)
    - "Ozark Mountain Party Games," by Vance Randolph and Nancy Clemens, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1933). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 230)
    - "Ozark Mountain Riddles," by Vance Randolph and Isabel Spradley, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1934). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 231)
    - "Ozark Superstitions," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1933). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 232)
    - "Prehistoric Inhabitants of Crawford County, Kansas," by Vernon C. Allison and Vance Randolph, reprinted from The American Anthropologist (July-September 1927). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 233)
    - Reviews of Frank Brown's The Frank Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore, by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (April-June 1953) and Mississippi Valley Historical Review (June 1953). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 234)
    - Review of John A. Lomax's Adventures of a Ballad Hunter, by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1948). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 235)
    - "Riddles from Arkansas," by Vance Randolph and Mary Celestia Parler, reprinted from Journal of American Folklore (July-September 1954). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 236)
    - "Tales from the Ozarks," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Western Folklore (January 1955). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 237)
    - "A Witch Trial in Carroll County," by Vance Randolph, reprinted from Arkansas Historical Quarterly (Spring 1957). (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 238)
    - Other authors. Contains journal articles and reviews not authored in whole or in part by Vance Randolph. Includes the authors Mary Celestia Parler, B.B. Ashcom, J. Frank Dobie, and H.C. Woodbridge. (Box 19 (oversize), Folder 239)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Note: Originals are contained in oversized Box 23 (Folder 240 to Folder 250) and in oversized Box 24 (Folder 251 to Folder 261); photocopies of these originals are located in Box 20.
    - Map of Kansas and Missouri, American Automobile Association, 1996. (Box 20, Folder 240)
    - Alcohol (Box 20, Folder 241)
    - Character sketches (Box 20, Folder 242)
    - Dialect (Box 20, Folder 243)
    - Folk belief and superstition (Box 20, Folder 244)
    - Guns and gunplay (Box 20, Folder 245)
    - Hidden treasure (1 of 2) (Box 20, Folder 246)
    - Hidden treasure (2 of 2) (Box 20, Folder 247)
    - Legend (Box 20, Folder 248)
    - Literature (Box 20, Folder 249)
    - Music (as subject) (Box 20, Folder 250)
    - Place-names (Box 20, Folder 251)
    - Politics (Box 20, Folder 252)
    - Prehistoric Ozarks (Box 20, Folder 253)
    - Randolph, Vance. Book reviews and articles authored by him. (Box 20, Folder 254)
    - Randolph, Vance (as subject) (Box 20, Folder 255)
    - Religion (Box 20, Folder 256)
    - Starr, Belle (Box 20, Folder 257)
    - Tall tales (Box 20, Folder 258)
    - Miscellaneous: neighborliness, death, sorghum making (Box 20, Folder 259)
    - Weather (Box 20, Folder 260)
    - Writing: Habits and methods of professional writers (Box 20, Folder 261)
- Series 2: Sound Recordings, Note: For song titles, see Archive of Folk Culture card catalog; photocopy in Folder 1c in this collection contains photocopies of catalog cards for 5236 A-5270 B3, an annotated manuscript of catalog entries for 5271 A1-5425 B3, an annotated list of fiddle tunes played by Lon Jordan (5314-5317, 5319-5326, 5376-5379, 5401-5402, 5404-5405), and two lists of fiddle tunes played by Bill Bilyeu (6897 A1-6904 B3).
  - 191 12-inch glass-based acetate records of original field recordings in the Ozarks, 1941-42; 5270, 5320, 5341, 5425 missing; 5300 broken. Duplicated on LWO 3493, reels 14-26. (5236-5425)
  - 4 16-inch, 45 12-inch, 2 10-inch, 5 8-inch glass and aluminum-based records of "Dear Mr. President," January and February 1942. 6398 missing; 6400 n/g; 6463 badly broken. Duplicated on LWO 3493, reel 42. (6397-6464)
  - 8 12-inch glass-based acetate records of original field recordings in the Ozarks, 1943; 6897 damaged; 6900 broken. Duplicated on LWO 3493, reels 56-57. (6897-6904)
  - "Some talk about Belle Starr." Contains the 5-inch reel-to-reel original master and a reference copy on a 60-minute audio cassette of an interview with Florence Watts. (Box 21, Folder 262)
- Series 3: Graphic Materials, Note: For a complete description of images, see Folder 1b: Log of Visual Images.
  - "Photos in Folksong MS, Dec., 1944.", Contains a list of photographs selected for inclusion in Ozark Folksongs (1946-50), including the name of the subject and the place of the photograph. Also contains front-and-back album covers entitled "Photographs of Singers." (Box 21, Folder 263)
  - Photographs 1-10., Contains 12 photoprints identified by subject and place, corresponding to the list in Folder 262. (Box 21, Folder 264)
  - Photographs 11-23., Contains 11 photoprints and 1 negative, identified by subject and place, corresponding to the list in Folder 262. (Box 21, Folder 265)
  - Photographs 24-35., Contains 12 photoprints and 1 negative, identified by subject and place, corresponding to the list in Folder 262. (Box 21, Folder 266)
  - Photographs 36-50., Contains 9 photoprints and 1 negative, identified by subject and place, corresponding to the list in Folder 262. (Box 21, Folder 267)
  - Photographs 51-60., Contains 11 photoprints and 1 negative, identified by subject and/or annotated. (Box 21, Folder 268)
  - Photographs 61-69.., Contains 11 photoprints, of which P61-64 are annotated and P65-67 are identified by subject (Box 21, Folder 269)
  - Photographs 70-83., Contains 14 photoprints, all unidentified. (Box 21, Folder 270)
  - Photographs 84-96., Contains 13 photoprints, of which P84-86 are unidentified, P87-92 are annotated, and P93-96 are identified by subject. (Box 22, Folder 271)
  - Photographs 97-102., Contains 6 photoprints, all unidentified. (Box 22, Folder 272)
  - Photographs 103-12., Contains 10 photoprints, all annotated. (Box 22, Folder 273)
  - Photographs 113-22., Contains 10 photoprints, of which only P121 is not annotated but identified by place. (Box 22, Folder 274)
  - Photographs 123-34., Contains 12 photoprints, all annotated. (Box 22, Folder 275)
  - Photographs 135-43., Contains 9 photoprints with annotations and 1 negative. (Box 22, Folder 276)
  - Photographs 144-47., Contains 4 photoprints and 2 negatives, all unidentified. (Box 22, Folder 277)
  - Photographs 148-58., Contains 9 photoprints, of which P148-51 are annotated and P154-56 are identified. Also contains 1 negative with a note from Ruth Tyler, a photocopy of the 1958 Folklore Institute photograph, and the annotated captions for 2 photographs. (Box 22, Folder 278)
  - Prints and Photographs Division, Lot 5580., Contains photographs 1-39 (photocopies of originals), most of which are tentatively identified. Described by subject, place, and visual image in Table B of the Log of Visual Images (Folder 1b). (Box 22, Folder 279)
  - Original Newspaper Clippings: A to N, Photocopies of these originals are in Box 20. (Box 23 (oversize))
  - Original Newspaper Clippings: O to Z, Photocopies of these originals are in Box 20. (Box 24 (oversize))
- Series 4: 2021 Accrual
  - Introduction (1 of 4), 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/1)
  - Introduction (2 of 4), 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/2)
  - Introduction (3 of 4), 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/3)
  - Introduction (4 of 4), 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/4)
  - Correspondence: Columbia Univ. Press, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/5)
  - Correspondence: Halpert, Herbert, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/6)
  - Correspondence: Other, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/7)
  - More jokes and head-notes, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/8)
  - The Man from Pyatt, Spring 1964, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/9)
  - Life among the Dragonflies, Little Blue Book #818, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/10)
  - Headnote material, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/11)
  - Photo prints of Vance Randolph, 3 photographic prints, black and white, various sizes (Box-folder 25/12)
Publications
Cochran, Robert. "Randolph, Vance." In American Folklore: An Encyclopedia. ed. Jan Harold Brunvand. 1996.
Cochran, Robert. Vance Randolph: An Ozark Life. 1985.
Articles by Vance Randolph
"Bedtime Stories from Missouri." Western Folklore X:1 (January 1951). Folder 217
"Book Review: Adventures of a Ballad Hunter." Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1948). Folder 235
"Book Review: The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore." Journal of American Folklore 66:260 (April-June 1953). Folder 234
"Book Review: The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore." The Mississippi Valley Historical Review (June 1953). Folder 235
"A Calendar of Kansas Butterflies." Entomological News, XL (March 1929). Folder 218
"Jump Rope Rhymes From Arkansas." Midwest Folklore III:2. (1953?) Folder 223
"Nakedness in Ozark Folk Belief." Journal of American Folklore 66:262 (October-December 1953). Folder 224
"The Names of Ozark Fiddle Tunes." Midwest Folklore IV:2 (1954). Folder 225
"On the Seasonal Migrations of Dione Vanillae in Kansas." Annals of the Entomological Society of America XX:2 (June 1927). Folder 228
Ozark Ghost Stories: Gruesome and Humorous Tales of the Supernatural in the Backwoods of the South. Girard, Kansas: Haldeman-Julius Publications, 1944. Folder 229
"Ozark Superstitions." Journal of American Folklore 46:179 (January-March 1933). Folder 232
"The Roots Go Deep." New York Times Book Review (November 17, 1963). Folder 226
"Tales from the Ozarks." Western Folklore XIV:1 (January 1955). Folder 237
"Tales From the Past, Some Tall, Some True." New York Times Book Review (January 3, 1960). Folder 226
"A Treasury to Draw Upon." New York Times Book Review (February 26, 1960). Folder 226
"A Witch Trial in Carroll County." Arkansas Historical Quarterly (Spring 1957). Folder 238
Co-Written Articles
Allison, Vernon C., and Vance Randoph. "Prehistoric Inhabitants of Crawford County, Kansas." American Anthropologist 29:3 (July-September 1927). Folder 233
Clemens, Nancy, and Vance Randolph. "Ozark Mountain Party-Games." Journal of American Folklore (January-March 1933) Folder 230
Emberson, Frances, and Vance Randolph. "The Collection of Folk Music in the Ozarks." Journal of American Folklore (April-June 1947). Folder 220
Hunter, Walter S., and Vance Randolph. "Further Studies of the Reliability of the Maze with Rants and Humans." Journal of Comparative Psychology IV:4 (August 1924). Folder 222
Hunter, Walter S., and Vance Randolph. "A Note on the Reliability of the Maze as a Method of Learning in the Angora Goat." The Pedagogical Seminary and Journal of Genetic Psychology XXXIII.I (March 1926). Folder 227
McCord, May Kennedy, and Vance Randolph. "Autograph Alhums in the Ozarks." Journal of American Folklore (April-June 1948). Folder 216
Musick, Ruth Ann, and Vance Randolph. "Children's Rhymes from Missouri." Journal of American Folklore (October-December 1950). Folder 219
Musick, Ruth Ann, and Vance Randolph. "Folksong Hunters in Missouri." Midwest Folklore (1951). Folder 221
Parler, Mary Celestia, and Vance Randolph. "Riddles from Arkansas." Journal of American Folklore 67:265 (July-September 1954). Folder 236
Spradley, Isabel, and Vance Randolph. "Ozark Mountain Riddle." Journal of American Folklore 47:183 (January-March 1934). Folder 231
Articles by Other Authors
Ashcom, B. B. "Notes on the Language of the Bedford, Pennsylvania, Suarea." American Speech XXVIII:4 (December 1953). Folder 239
Dobie, J. Frank. The Mezcla Man. El Paso, Texas: El Paso del Norte, 1954. Folder 239
Parler, Mary Celestia. "The Forty-Mile Jumper." Journal of American Folklore 64:254 (422-23) (October-December 1951). Folder 239
Woodbridge, Hensley C. "Folklore in the Works of Janice Holt Giles." The Register of the Kentucky Historical Society (October 1957). Folder 239